

Senior Researcher | Department of Computer Science | ETH Zurich

□+41 764999105 | ☑ si.liu@inf.ethz.ch | 😭 siliunobi.github.io

Research Interests _____

Si Liu's research interests encompass formal methods (FM), software engineering (SE), and distributed systems, with a particular emphasis on **applying FM and SE techniques to build reliable, secure, and efficient distributed systems**. His current work focuses on verifying and validating the **designs & deployments** of databases and DNS, addressing both **qualitative** (e.g., reliability and security) **& quantitative** (e.g., availability and scalability) aspects. He has also recently developed an interest in verifying AI-powered systems.

Education	
University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign (UIUC) PHD IN COMPUTER SCIENCE • Advisor: Prof. Dr. Jose Meseguer	Aug. 2012 – May 2019
East China Normal University (ECNU) MASTER IN COMPUTER SCIENCE	Sep. 2009 - May 2012
East China Normal University (ECNU) BACHELOR IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING	Sep. 2005 – Jun. 2009
Professional Experience	
May 2023 – Present Aug. 2019 – May 2023 Oct. 2014 – Sep. 2018 Jun. 2011 – Aug. 2011 Sep. 2009 – May 2012 Research Assistant, Assured Cloud Computing Center, UIUC Research Intern, National Cyber-Physical Systems Camp, USTC Research Assistant, Danish-Chinese Research Center, ECNU Software Engineering Intern, Dept. of Talent House, Hewlett-Pack	ard Co. Ltd.
Awards & Honors	
Grant for Project "Formal Verification of Isolation Guarantees in Database Systems" (official project partner), SNSF (Swiss National Science Foundati Career Seed Award, ETH Zurich The ETH Medal for supervised Master thesis (Top 2.5%), ETH Zurich The ETH Medal for supervised Master thesis (Top 2.5%), ETH Zurich Outstanding Graduate Award (Ranked 1st), East China Normal University Excellent Student Award (Ranked 1st), East China Normal University	

* I contributed equally as a co-first author † indicates the students I supervised

• FM/SE x DATABASES

Under Submission:

Publications ___

[VLDB'25] Zijing Yin[†], Si Liu, David Basin. Testing Graph Databases with Synthesized Queries [—'25] Si Liu*, Zhiheng Cai*, Hengfeng Wei. Uniso: A Unified Framework for Checking Database Isolation Guarantees

OCTOBER 2024 SI LIU · CURRICULUM VITAE

- [-'25] Shabnam Ghasemirad[†], Christoph Sprenger, **Si Liu**, Luca Multazzu, David Basin. Pushing the Limit: Verified Performance-Optimal Causally Consistent Database Transactions
- [-'25] Jiang Xiao[†], **Si Liu**, Hengfeng Wei. Boosting Database Isolation Checking via Mini-Transactions

Under Revision:

[VLDB'25] Shabnam Ghasemirad[†], **Si Liu**, Luca Multazzu, Christoph Sprenger, David Basin. VerIso: Verifiable Isolation Guarantees for Database Transactions

Published:

- [OOPSLA'24] Si Liu, Long Gu, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin. Plume: Efficient and Complete Black-box Checking of Weak Isolation Levels
- [SIGMOD'24] Si Liu, Luca Multazzu, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin. NOC-NOC: Towards Performance-optimal Distributed Transactions
 - [VLDB'24] Long Gu[†], Si Liu, Tiancheng Xing, Hengfeng Wei, Yuxing Chen, David Basin. IsoVista: Black-box Checking Database Isolation Guarantees. **Demo Track**
 - [VLDB'23] Si Liu*, Kaile Huang*, Zhenge Chen, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin, Haixiang Li, Anqun Pan. Efficient Black-box Checking of Snapshot Isolation in Databases
 - [OSDI'23] Zu-Ming Jiang, Si Liu, Manuel Rigger, Zhendong Su. Detecting Transactional Bugs in Database Engines via Graph-Based Oracle Construction
- [OOPSLA'22] Si Liu, Jose Meseguer, Peter Csaba Olveczky, Min Zhang, David Basin. Bridging the Semantic Gap between Qualitative and Quantitative Models of Distributed Systems
- [TOSEM'22] Si Liu. All in One: Design, Verification, and Implementation of SNOW-Optimal Read Atomic Transactions

• FM x DNS (AND BEYOND)

Under Submission:

[-'25] Dhruv Nevatia[†], Si Liu, David Basin. Reachability Analysis of the Domain Name System

Published:

- [USENIX SEC'24] Huayi Duan, Marco Bearzi, Jodok Vieli, Adrian Perrig, David Basin, Si Liu, Bernhard Tellenbach. CAMP: Compositional Amplification Attacks against DNS
 - [SIGCOMM'23] Si Liu, Huayi Duan, Lukas Heimes, Marco Bearzi, Jodok Vieli, Adrian Perrig, David Basin. A Formal Framework for End-to-End DNS Resolution
 - [NSDI'23] Huayi Duan, Fischer Ruben, Lou Jie, Si Liu, David Basin, Adrian Perrig. RHINE: Robust and Highperformance Internet Naming with E2E Authenticity
 - [CSF'22] Si Liu*, Thilo Weghorn*, Christoph Sprenger, Adrian Perrig, David Basin. N-Tube: Formally Verified Secure Bandwidth Reservation in Path-Aware Internet Architectures
- [Book Chapter] David Basin, Tobias Klenze, Si Liu, Christoph Sprenger. Design-Level Verification in The Complete Guide to SCION: From Design Principles to Formal Verification. 2022
- [Book Chapter] Giacomo Giuliari, Markus Legner, Si Liu, Adrian Perrig, Thilo Weghorn, Marc Wyss. Extensions for the Data Plane in The Complete Guide to SCION: From Design Principles to Formal Verification. 2022

• FM/SE x AI

Under Submission:

[—'25] Shi Peng, **Si Liu**, Peixin Wang, Chenyang Xu, Cheng Chen, Dapeng Zhi, Min Zhang. ATA: An Abstract-Train-Abstract Approach for Explanation-Friendly Deep Reinforcement Learning

Published:

- [CAV'24] Dapeng Zhi, Peixin Wang, Si Liu, Luke Ong, Min Zhang. Unifying Qualitative and Quantitative Safety Verification of DNN-Controlled Systems
- **[VMCAI'24]** Jiaxu Tian, Dapeng Zhi, **Si Liu**, Peixin Wang, Guy Katz, Min Zhang. Taming Reachability Analysis of DNN-Controlled Systems via Abstraction-Based Training
- [NeurlPS'23] Jiaxu Tian, Dapeng Zhi, Si Liu, Peixin Wang, Cheng Chen, Min Zhang. Boosting Verification of Deep Reinforcement Learning via Piece-Wise Linear Decision Neural Networks
 - [CVPR'23] Zhaodi Zhang, Zhiyi Xue, Yang Chen, Si Liu, Yueling Zhang, Jing Liu, Min Zhang. Boosting Verified Training for Robust Image Classifications via Abstraction
 - [ISSTA'23] Zhiyi Xue, Si Liu, Zhaodi Zhang, Yiting Wu, Min Zhang. A Tale of Two Approximations: Tightening Over-Approximation for DNN Robustness Verification via Under-Approximation
 - [ASE'22] Zhaodi Zhang, Yiting Wu, Si Liu, Jing Liu, Min Zhang. Provably Tightest Linear Approximation for Robustness Verification of Sigmoid-like Neural Networks

PRIOR TO 2022:

- [TASE'21] Lei Liang, Si Liu. Exploring Design Alternatives for Replicated RAMP Transactions Using Maude
- [NFM'20] Si Liu, Atul Sandur, Jose Meseguer, Peter Olveczky, Qi Wang. Generating Correct-by-Construction Distributed Implementations from Formal Maude Designs
- **[TACAS'19] Si Liu**, Peter Csaba Olveczky, Min Zhang, Qi Wang, Jose Meseguer. Automatic Analysis of Consistency Properties of Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude.
- [FAoC'19] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Qi Wang, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Read Atomic Transactions with Prevention of Lost Updates: ROLA and Its Formal Analysis. Formal Aspects of Computing
 - [CCS'19] Qi Wang, Pubali Datta, Wei Yang, Si Liu, Carl Gunter, Adam Bates. Charting the Attack Surface of Trigger-Action IoT Platforms.
- [FASE'18] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Keshav Santhanam, Qi Wang, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. ROLA: A New Distributed Transaction Protocol and Its Formal Analysis.
- [LITES'17] Si Liu, Jatin Ganhotra, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Son Nguyen, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. *Leibniz Transactions on Embedded Systems*
- [ICFEM'17] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Jatin Ganhotra, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Exploring Design Alternatives for RAMP Transactions through Statistical Model Checking.
- [**JLAMP'16**] **Si Liu**, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, José Meseguer. Modeling and Analyzing Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude. *Journal of Logical and Algebraic Methods in Programming*
 - [SAC'16] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Jatin Ganhotra, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems.
- [QEST'15] Si Liu, Son Nguyen, Jatin Ganhotra, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. *Nominated for Best Paper.*
- [ICFEM'14] Si Liu, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Stephen Skeirik, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of Cassandra in Maude.
- [PRDC'14] Xi Wu, Si Liu, Huibiao Zhu and Yongxin Zhao. Reasoning about Group-Based Mobility in MANETs.
- [ComSIS'13] Xi Wu, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, Zheng Wang, Si Liu. Modeling and verifying the Ariadne protocol using process algebra. Computer Science and Information Systems Journal
 - [ECBS'12] Xi Wu, Si Liu, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, Lei Chen. Modeling and Verifying the Ariadne Protocol Using CSP.
 - [HASE'11] Si Liu, Yongxin Zhao, Huibiao Zhu, Qin Li. A Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks from a Group Probabilistic Perspective.
 - [SSIRI'11] Si Liu, Xiaofeng Wu, Qin Li, Huibiao Zhu, Qian Wang. Formal Approaches to Wireless Sensor Networks.
 - [TASE'11] Si Liu, Yongxin Zhao, Huibiao Zhu, Qin Li. Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks.

- **[TASE'11]** Mengying Wang, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, **Si Liu**. Modeling and Analyzing the μ TESLA Protocol Using CSP.
- [ICECCS'11] Yongxin Zhao, Yanhong Huang, Jifeng He, Si Liu. Formal Model of Interrupt Program from a Probabilistic Perspective.
 - [UTP'10] Qin Li, Yongxin Zhao, Xiaofeng Wu, Si Liu. Promoting Models.

WORKSHOP PAPERS

- [WRLA'18] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Qi Wang, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of the Walter Transactional Data Store.
 - [SSS'15] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky and José Meseguer. Formal analysis of Leader Election in MANETs Using Real-Time Maude.
- [WRLA'14] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky and José Meseguer. A Framework for Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude.
- [SSIRI'11] Han Zhu, Huibiao Zhu, Si Liu, Jian Guo. Towards Denotational Semantics for Verilog in PVS.

OTHER BOOK CHAPTERS

• Rakesh Bobba, Jon Grov, Indranil Gupta, **Si Liu**, José Meseguer, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Stephen Skeirik. Survivability: Design, Formal Modeling, and Validation of Cloud Storage Systems using Maude. 2018.

PHD THESIS

• Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign. 2019

Teaching Experience _____

Fall 2024	Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2024	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2023	Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2023	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2022	Information Systems for Engineers, Head Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2022	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2021	Applied Security Lab, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2021	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2020	Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2020	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2019	Applied Security Lab, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2016	Distributed Systems, Teaching Assistant	UIUC
Fall 2011	Process Algebra, Teaching Assistant	ECNU
Spring 2011	Algorithms and Data Structures, Teaching Assistant	ECNU
Fall 2010	Discrete Mathematics, Teaching Assistant	ECNU
Spring 2010	Algorithms and Data Structures, Teaching Assistant	ECNU

Mentoring _____

PhD students

- Dhruv Nevatia (co-supervised with Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich
- Shabnam Ghasemirad (co-supervised with Dr. Christoph Sprenger and Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich
- Zijing Yin (co-supervised with Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich

- Ziwei Zhou (co-supervised with Prof. Min Zhang), ECNU
- Shi Peng (co-supervised with Prof. Min Zhang), ECNU
- Zhaodi Zhang (co-supervised with Prof. Min Zhang; first employment: Chengdu Education Research Institute), ECNU

Graduate students

- Theodor Moroianu, ETH Zurich
- Yunxin Sun, ETH Zurich
- Yufei Zhang, ETH Zurich
- Rolando Grave de Peralta, ETH Zurich
- Zhou Zhou, ECNU
- Long Gu, Nanjing University
- Qiuhuan Xiong, Nanjing University
- Luca Multazz (first employment: SICPA), ETH Zurich
 - * honoured with the ETH Medal for his Master thesis "NOCS-Optimal Distributed Transactions and Beyon" (top 2.5%)
- Lukas Heimes (first employment: SBB CFF FFS), ETH Zurich
 - * honoured with the ETH Medal for his Master thesis "A Formal Framework for End-to-End DNS Resolution" (top 2.5%)
- Jodok Vieli (graduated), ETH Zurich
- Marco Bearzi (graduated), ETH Zurich
- Shabnam Ghasemirad (now PhD at ETH Zurich), ETH Zurich
- Jiang Xiao (first employment: Agricultural Bank of China), Nanjing University
- Teng Wang (first employment: Alibaba Cloud), Nanjing University
- Jiaxu Tian (first employment: CITIC Securities), ECNU
- Zhiyi Xue (now PhD at ECNU), ECNU

Undergraduate students

- Tiancheng Xing (graduated, now Master at NUS), Nanjing University
- Zhiheng Cai (graduated, now PhD at Tsinghua University), Nanjing University
- Long Gu (graduated, now Master at Nanjing University), Nanjing University
- Zhenge Chen (graduated, now Master at UCSD), Nanjing University
- Zhou Zhou (graduated, now Master at ECNU), ECNU
- Ziwei Zhou (graduated, now PhD at ECNU), ECNU
- Ruiyang Liu (graduated, now Master at JHU), ECNU
- Lei Liang (graduated, now at CITIC Securities), ECNU
- Plamen Stefanov (graduated, now Master at ETH Zurich), ETH Zurich

- Keshav Santhanam (graduated, now PhD at Stanford University), UIUC

Professional Activities

- Program Committee Member: NSDI'25, ICFEM'24, ICFEM'23
- Journal Reviewer: JLAMP, SCP, The VLDB Journal
- Sub-Reviewer: ICFEM ('22, '16, '14, '13, '12, '11, '10), FM ('21, '18), FASE'14, TASE ('12, '11)
- Dagstuhl Seminar: "Ensuring the Reliability and Robustness of Database Management Systems (21442)"
 2021 (participant)
- **Grant Proposal:** preparing proposal for NSF CNS 1409416 (\$584,508; 2014–2018), Availability-Consistency Tradeoffs in Key-Value and NoSQL Storage Systems

Talks & Presentations _____

- NOC-NOC: Towards Performance-optimal Distributed Transactions. SIGMOD'24, Santiago, Chile, 2024.
- Generating Correct-by-Construction Distributed Implementations from Formal Maude Designs. NFM'20, Virtual, 2020.
- Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. University Paris Diderot, France, 2019.
- Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. ETH Zurich, Switzerland, 2019.
- Automatic Analysis of Consistency Properties of Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. TACAS'19, Prague, Czech Republic, 2019.
- Exploring Design Alternatives for RAMP Transactions through Statistical Model Checking. ICFEM'17, Xi'an, China, 2017.
- Design, Formal Modeling, and Validation of Cloud Storage Systems using Maude. Huawei, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2017.
- Exploring Design Alternatives for the RAMP Transaction System Through Statistical Model Checking. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2017.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems. SAC'16, Pisa, Italy, 2016.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2016.
- Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. QEST'15, Madrid, Spain, 2015.
- Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2015.
- A Framework for Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude. WRLA'14, Grenoble, France, 2014.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Cassandra in Maude. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2014.
- A Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks from a Group Probabilistic Perspective. HASE'11, Boca Raton, USA, 2011.
- Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks. USTC, Suzhou, China, 2011.

- Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks. TASE'11, Xi'an, China, 2011.
- Formal Approaches to Wireless Sensor Networks. SSIRI'11, Jeju Island, Korea, 2011.